<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Don&#39;t Panic</title>
    <link>http://commaok.xyz/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Don&#39;t Panic</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 10:52:40 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://commaok.xyz/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Logging, interfaces, and allocation</title>
      <link>http://commaok.xyz/post/interface-allocs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 10:52:40 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://commaok.xyz/post/interface-allocs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is about some new compiler optimizations scheduled for Go 1.9,
but I want to start with logging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, Peter Bourgon started a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/golang-dev/F3l9Iz1JX4g&#34;&gt;thread on golang-dev about standardizing logging&lt;/a&gt;.
Logging is pervasive, so performance came up quickly.
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/go-kit/kit/tree/master/log&#34;&gt;go-kit log package&lt;/a&gt; uses structured logging,
centered on this interface:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;type Logger interface {
    Log(keyvals ...interface{}) error
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample call:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;logger.Log(&amp;quot;transport&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;HTTP&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;addr&amp;quot;, addr, &amp;quot;msg&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;listening&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that everything that goes into a logging call gets converted into an interface.
This means that it allocates a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare with another structured logger, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/uber-go/zap&#34;&gt;zap&lt;/a&gt;.
Zap has uglier call sites, specifically to avoid using interfaces, in order to be zero-allocation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;logger.Info(&amp;quot;Failed to fetch URL.&amp;quot;,
  zap.String(&amp;quot;url&amp;quot;, url),
  zap.Int(&amp;quot;attempt&amp;quot;, tryNum),
  zap.Duration(&amp;quot;backoff&amp;quot;, sleepFor),
)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments to &lt;code&gt;logger.Info&lt;/code&gt; have type &lt;code&gt;logger.Field&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;logger.Field&lt;/code&gt; is a kind of union-ish struct
that includes a type and a field each for a &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt;, an &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;, and an &lt;code&gt;interface{}&lt;/code&gt;.
Thus interfaces are not necessary to pass the most common kinds of values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about logging. Why does converting a concrete value to an interface sometime allocate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interfaces are represented as two words, a type pointer and a value pointer.
Russ Cox wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://research.swtch.com/interfaces&#34;&gt;lovely explanation of this&lt;/a&gt;,
which I will not attempt to repeat. Just go read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His post is slightly out of date, however.
He points out an obvious optimization: When the value is pointer-sized or smaller,
we can just put the value directly into the second interface word.
However, with the advent of concurrent garbage collection,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/issue/8405&#34;&gt;that optimization got eliminated&lt;/a&gt;.
Now the second word in the interface is always a pointer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;fmt.Println(1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Go 1.4, this code did not allocate,
because the value &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; could be put directly into the second interface word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, the compiler treated it something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;fmt.Println({int, 1})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;{typ, val}&lt;/code&gt; represents the two words in an interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of Go 1.4, this code started allocating, because &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; is not a pointer,
and the second word must contain a pointer.
So instead the compiler+runtime conspired to turn it into something roughly like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;i := new(int) // allocates!
*i = 1
fmt.Println({int, i})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was painful, and there was much wringing of hands and gnashing of teeth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/golang/go/commit/22701339817a591cd352ecd43b0439b84dbe8095&#34;&gt;first significant optimization to remove allocations&lt;/a&gt;
was added a bit later. It kicked in when the resulting interface did not escape.
In that case, the temporary value could be put on the stack instead of the heap.
Using our example code above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;i := new(int) // now doesn&#39;t allocate, as long as e doesn&#39;t escape
*i = 1
var e interface{} = {int, i}
// do things with e that don&#39;t make it escape
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, many interfaces do escape, including those used in calls
to &lt;code&gt;fmt.Println&lt;/code&gt; and in our logging examples above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily, Go 1.9 will bring a few more optimizations,
in part inspired by the logging conversation.
(Unless those optimizations get reverted in the next six months,
which is always a possibility.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first optimization is &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/issue/18704&#34;&gt;to not allocate to convert a constant to an interface&lt;/a&gt;.
So &lt;code&gt;fmt.Println(1)&lt;/code&gt; will no longer allocate. The compiler puts
the value &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; in a readonly global, roughly like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;var i int = 1 // at the top level, marked as readonly

fmt.Println({int, &amp;amp;i})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is possible because constants are immutable,
and will thus be the same every time the interface conversion is reached,
including recursively and concurrently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was inspired directly by the logging discussion.
In structured logging, many of the arguments are constants&amp;ndash;
almost certainly all the keys, and probably a few of the values.
Recall the go-kit example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;logger.Log(&amp;quot;transport&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;HTTP&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;addr&amp;quot;, addr, &amp;quot;msg&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;listening&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This code drops from 6 allocations to 1, because five of the arguments are constant strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second new optimization is &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/issue/17725&#34;&gt;to not allocate to convert bools and bytes to interfaces&lt;/a&gt;.
This optimization works by adding a global &lt;code&gt;[256]byte&lt;/code&gt; array called &lt;code&gt;staticbytes&lt;/code&gt; to every binary,
where &lt;code&gt;staticbytes[b] = b&lt;/code&gt; for all b.
When the compiler wants to put a bool or uint8 or other single-byte value
into an interface, instead of allocating, it calculates a pointer into this array.
That is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;var staticbytes [256]byte = {0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, ...}

i := uint8(1)
fmt.Println({uint8, &amp;amp;staticbytes[i]})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a third new optimization proposed that is still under review,
which is &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/cl/36476&#34;&gt;to not allocate to convert common zero values in an interface&lt;/a&gt;.
It applies to integers, floats, strings, and slices.
This optimization works by checking at runtime whether the value is &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt;).
If so, it uses a pointer to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/golang/go/blob/go1.8rc3/src/runtime/hashmap.go#L1182&#34;&gt;an existing large chunk of zeroed memory&lt;/a&gt;
rather than allocating some memory and zeroing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all goes well, Go 1.9 should eliminate a fair number of allocations during interface conversions.
But it won&amp;rsquo;t eliminate all of them, which leaves performance still on the table as the logging discussion continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interplay between implementation decisions and APIs is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picking an API requires thinking about the performance consequences.
It is not an accident that &lt;code&gt;io.Reader&lt;/code&gt; requires/allows callers to bring their own buffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance is in no small part a consequence of the implementation decisions.
We have seen in this post that the implementation details of interfaces can substantially alter
what code allocates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet those very implementation decisions depend on what kind of code people write.
The compiler and runtime authors want to optimize real, common code.
For example, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/issue/8405&#34;&gt;decision to in Go 1.4 to keep interface values at two words instead of changing them to three&lt;/a&gt;,
which made &lt;code&gt;fmt.Println(1)&lt;/code&gt; allocate, was based on looking at the kind of code people wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the kind of code people write is often shaped heavily by the APIs they use,
we have the kind of organic feedback loop that is fascinating and sometimes challenging to manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a terribly deep observation, perhaps, but there is one takeaway:
If you&amp;rsquo;re designing an API and worrying about performance,
keep in mind not just what the existing compiler and runtime actually do,
but what they could do.
Write code for the present, but design APIs for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you&amp;rsquo;re not sure, ask. It worked (a bit) for logging.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Picking up pennies: Disabling memory profiling</title>
      <link>http://commaok.xyz/post/memprofilerate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 18:06:36 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://commaok.xyz/post/memprofilerate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you work on a short-lived, allocation heavy program
and care about a tiny (maybe 0.5%) performance improvement,
this post is for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was looking at a CPU profile of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/cmd/compile/&#34;&gt;Go compiler&lt;/a&gt;
when I noticed something odd: An entry in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/golang/go/blob/go1.8rc3/src/runtime/mprof.go&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mprof.go&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;mprof.go&lt;/code&gt; contains the memory profiling implementation, but I was doing cpu profiling.
Was there a bug in &lt;a href=&#34;https://godoc.org/rsc.io/compilebench&#34;&gt;compilebench&lt;/a&gt;, perhaps?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope. The variable &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/pkg/runtime/#pkg-variables&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;runtime.MemProfileRate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
controls the rate at which the runtime samples allocations.
And its default value is not 0 (disabled), but &lt;code&gt;512 * 1024&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a good default.
One sample per 500k of allocations is not much overhead.
And when something goes wrong on a server, you want to be able to find out why,
rather than fussing with profiling settings and then hoping it happens again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you work on a short-lived program, like a compiler,
when something goes wrong, you probably don&amp;rsquo;t have any mechanism for gathering ad hoc profiles.
For any given run, you either have profiling enabled or you don&amp;rsquo;t,
and if something goes wrong, you just enable profiling and try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if your program is allocation-heavy, like the Go compiler,
there might be enough memory profiling samples collected to absorb some CPU time.
(As currently implemented, the first sample is particularly expensive,
as it allocates a pretty large data structure.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m always looking for performance wins in the compiler, even little ones (hoping they add up).
So I sent a CL to &lt;a href=&#34;https://go-review.googlesource.com/c/35916/&#34;&gt;disable memory profiling entirely when not explicitly requested&lt;/a&gt;.
The benefits aren&amp;rsquo;t head-turning, but it&amp;rsquo;s a very cheap, low risk 0.5% to put in the bank.
It&amp;rsquo;ll get reviewed for Go 1.9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this in your own program requires nothing more than setting
&lt;code&gt;runtime.MemProfileRate = 0&lt;/code&gt; when memory profiling has not been requested.
But please, think twice first.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compile-time assertions in Go</title>
      <link>http://commaok.xyz/post/compile-time-assertions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 09:37:05 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://commaok.xyz/post/compile-time-assertions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is about a little-known way to make compile-time assertions in Go.
You probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t use it, but it is interesting to know about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a warm-up, here&amp;rsquo;s a fairly well-known form of compile-time assertions in Go: Interface satisfaction checks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this code (&lt;a href=&#34;https://play.golang.org/p/MJ6zF1oNsX&#34;&gt;playground&lt;/a&gt;),
the &lt;code&gt;var _ =&lt;/code&gt; line ensures that type &lt;code&gt;W&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;code&gt;stringWriter&lt;/code&gt;,
as checked for by &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/pkg/io/#WriteString&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;io.WriteString&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;package main

import &amp;quot;io&amp;quot;

type W struct{}

func (w W) Write(b []byte) (int, error)       { return len(b), nil }
func (w W) WriteString(s string) (int, error) { return len(s), nil }

type stringWriter interface {
	WriteString(string) (int, error)
}

var _ stringWriter = W{}

func main() {
	var w W
	io.WriteString(w, &amp;quot;very long string&amp;quot;)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you comment out &lt;code&gt;W&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;WriteString&lt;/code&gt; method, the code will not compile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;main.go:14: cannot use W literal (type W) as type stringWriter in assignment:
	W does not implement stringWriter (missing WriteString method)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is useful. For most types that satisfy both &lt;code&gt;io.Writer&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;stringWriter&lt;/code&gt;,
if you eliminate the &lt;code&gt;WriteString&lt;/code&gt; method, everything will continue to work
as it did before, but with worse performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than trying to write a fragile test for a performance regression using
&lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/pkg/testing/#AllocsPerRun&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;testing.T.AllocsPerRun&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
you can simply protect your code with a compile-time assertion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/golang/go/blob/go1.8rc2/src/io/multi.go#L72&#34;&gt;a real world example of this technique from package io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, onward to obscurity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interface satisfaction checks are great.
But what if you wanted to check a plain old boolean expression, like &lt;code&gt;1+1==2&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this code (&lt;a href=&#34;https://play.golang.org/p/mjIMWsWu4V&#34;&gt;playground&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;package main

import &amp;quot;crypto/md5&amp;quot;

type Hash [16]byte

func init() {
	if len(Hash{}) &amp;lt; md5.Size {
		panic(&amp;quot;Hash is too small&amp;quot;)
	}
}

func main() {
	// ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Hash&lt;/code&gt; is perhaps some kind of abstracted hash result.
The &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; function ensures that it will work with &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/pkg/crypto/md5/&#34;&gt;crypto/md5&lt;/a&gt;.
If you change &lt;code&gt;Hash&lt;/code&gt; to be (say) &lt;code&gt;[8]byte&lt;/code&gt;, it&amp;rsquo;ll panic when the process starts.
However, this is a run-time check.
What if we wanted it to fail earlier?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how. (There&amp;rsquo;s no playground link, because this doesn&amp;rsquo;t work on the playground.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;package main

import &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;

import &amp;quot;crypto/md5&amp;quot;

type Hash [16]byte

func hashIsTooSmall()

func init() {
	if len(Hash{}) &amp;lt; md5.Size {
		hashIsTooSmall()
	}
}

func main() {
	// ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you change &lt;code&gt;Hash&lt;/code&gt; to be &lt;code&gt;[8]byte&lt;/code&gt;, it will fail during compilation.
(Actually, it fails during linking. Close enough for our purposes.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ go build .
# demo
main.hashIsTooSmall: call to external function
main.init.1: relocation target main.hashIsTooSmall not defined
main.init.1: undefined: &amp;quot;main.hashIsTooSmall&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;hashIsTooSmall&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/ref/spec#Function_declarations&#34;&gt;declared without a function body&lt;/a&gt;.
The compiler assumes that someone else will provide an implementation,
perhaps an assembly routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the compiler can prove that &lt;code&gt;len(Hash{}) &amp;lt; md5.Size&lt;/code&gt;,
it eliminates the code inside the if statement.
As a result, no one uses the function &lt;code&gt;hashIsTooSmall&lt;/code&gt;,
so the linker eliminates it. No harm done.
As soon as the assertion fails, the code inside the if statement is preserved.
&lt;code&gt;hashIsTooSmall&lt;/code&gt; can&amp;rsquo;t be eliminated.
The linker then notices that no one else has provided an implementation
for the function and fails with an error, which was the goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last oddity: Why &lt;code&gt;import &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;?
The go tool knows that in normal Go code, all functions must have bodies,
and instructs the compiler to enforce that.
By switching to cgo, we remove that check.
(If you run &lt;code&gt;go build -x&lt;/code&gt; on the code above, without the &lt;code&gt;import &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; line,
you will see that the compiler is invoked with the &lt;code&gt;-complete&lt;/code&gt; flag.)
An alternative to adding &lt;code&gt;import &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; is to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/golang/go/blob/go1.8rc2/src/os/signal/sig.s&#34;&gt;add an empty file called &lt;code&gt;foo.s&lt;/code&gt;
to the package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know of only one use of this technique,
in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/golang/go/blob/go1.8rc2/test/fixedbugs/issue9608.dir/issue9608.go&#34;&gt;compiler test suite&lt;/a&gt;.
There are other &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/golang/go/blob/go1.8rc2/src/runtime/hashmap.go#L261&#34;&gt;imaginable places to apply it&lt;/a&gt;,
but no one has bothered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s probably how it should be. :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>new(Blog)</title>
      <link>http://commaok.xyz/post/new-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 15:19:05 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://commaok.xyz/post/new-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to try this blogging thing again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve failed at it a few times before.
I&amp;rsquo;m going to try &lt;a href=&#34;https://jvns.ca/blog/2016/05/22/how-do-you-write-blog-posts/&#34;&gt;Julia Evans&lt;/a&gt; style this time.
Maybe this one will stick?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>